בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is קט"ו Kuf Tes Vav
and we pick up at the very first word of קט"ו Kuf
Tes Vav
and the issue at stake here is the radical statement of רבי
יוחנן Reb Yochanan in the name of רבי יהודה בר רבי שמעון
Reb Yehuda bar Reb Shimon that a mother can, that if a
son dies, his mother inherits from him against the משנה. Mishna. And
not only is it radical, I think I said disruptive, it's radical
in that it's against the משנה Mishna and that it's like does
not have a clear basis in the פסוקים, Psukim, although he learns
it out from the word מטות. Matot.
But it's highly disruptive and as תוספות Tosfot points out that then
it just leads for property regularly going away from the sort of
father's family and from the tribe, etc. All the, it takes the
sort of innovation of בנות צלפחד B'not Tzelofchad and it just like
squares it. So now it has it not only passing down to
daughters, but also passing up to mothers and so on. Anyway, that's
the statement. So now let's take a look what the, and because
of that radical nature of it, תוספות Tosfot wants to try to
say that that was limited to a case of like a גר
Ger where there would be no father's family for it to pass
to. But that's certainly not the פשט Pshat of the גמרא. Gemara.
So let's take a look at the top of קט"ו. Kuf Tes
Vav. איתי רבי יוחנן לרבי יהודה בר רבי שמעון. Eisei Reb Yochanan
l'Reb Yehuda bar Reb Shimon. So this is what רבי יוחנן Reb
Yochanan reported in the name of רבי יהודה בר רבי שמעון, Reb
Yehuda bar Reb Shimon, but now he himself challenged this teaching which
is our משנה. Mishna. איש את בניו ואשה את בעלה ואחי האם,
Ish es benav, isha es ba'alah, v'achei ha'eim, a woman and her
son, wife and her husband, and the uncles, מנחילין ולא נוחלין, Manchilin
v'lo nochlin, they can bequeath but they won't inherit. So a wife
doesn't inherit from her husband and a mother doesn't inherit from her
son. It's explicit in the משנה Mishna against this teaching. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ולימא ליה... V'leima lei...
I'm sorry, excuse me, I skipped a line. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so רבי יהודה בר רבי שמעון Reb Yehuda bar Reb Shimon said
to him, משנתנו איני יודע מי שנאה. Mishnasenu eini yodeia mi shenasnah.
Yeah, I don't know who taught that משנה, Mishna, that's not my
opinion. Okay, so basically like, yeah, there's some תנא Tanna that holds
that way, who knows who that is, but I disagree with that
משנה. Mishna. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ולימא ליה, V'leima lei,
רבי זכריה בן הקצב Reb Zechariah ben HaKatzav דלא דריש מטות. d'lo
darish matot.
So you know, as long as you're going to go ahead and
say that the משנה Mishna is a more דעת יחיד, da'as yachid,
right, not a consensus opinion but a, you know, thank you, a
separate opinion of one תנא Tanna or something, rather than saying like,
oh, some random person holds that way, that's not the consensus, why
don't you actually identify who the תנא Tanna is? Who's the תנא?
Tanna? רבי זכריה בן הקצב. Reb Zechariah ben HaKatzav. If you remember,
רבי זכריה בן הקצב Reb Zechariah ben HaKatzav said that דרשה drasha
of מטות, matot, right, we learned כל בת יורשת נחלה ממטות, Kol
bat yoreshes nachala mi'matot,
we sort of said the דרשה drasha of מטות matot in the
plural described a scenario in which the daughter was, that her father
was from one tribe and her mother was from another, and it
equated the tribe of the father to the tribe of the mother.
Now in what degree did it equate them? So before the question
was the issue of what do you call it, of whether, of
whether when a woman dies and her property passes down to her
children, do the daughters come first, do the daughters come after the
sons, or since it's the mother's property and not the father's property,
maybe the daughters and the sons inherit equally? You remember that very
interesting idea once you're not dealing with the father's property, so you
don't have to sort of maintain, you don't have to necessarily maintain
the patriarchy, so therefore maybe the daughters and the sons can inherit
equally? So that was a question. And the argument that they did
not was, no no no, it says מטות, matot, that the mother's
tribe is like the father's tribe, it equates them. So the same
way by the father's tribe the sons get first, when it comes
down through the mother the sons get first. Okay, that was that
דרשה. drasha. But
רבי זכריה בן הקצב, Reb Zechariah ben HaKatzav, he rejected that, and
he said that no, I don't hold equating the mother's tribe and
the father's tribe, and I say that the daughters inherit equally with
the sons when the mother dies. Okay, so the key point is
here, it's a little confusing because it's not like these דרשות drashos
line up, one is more pro-feminist and the other is less or
whatever. I mean because there's two issues, right? So
מטות matot is מטה האם mateh ha'eim
equals
מטה האב, mateh ha'av, that's the דרשה. drasha. So what is the
implications of that דרשה? drasha? So one implication of that דרשה drasha
is that when the mother dies,
mother dies, the sons get first, sons get first, right? Because just
like when the father dies. So one implication of equating the two
is that when the mother dies the sons get first. The other
implication of equating the two, if you hold of this idea we
learned when a son dies, the same way his father inherits his
mother inherits, because it equates the two.
So if a son dies, mother inherits, mother inherits, okay, together with
the father if there is no living father. All right, so notice
here, right, this is privileges sons, right, and this here sort
of...
This
is more likely to happen.
Okay, so if the son predeceases the mother, that land leaves the
line
of the father and goes to the line of the mother
if the father's already dead. Right, exactly. So they come go and
point in different directions if you're sort of thinking from a women's
rights type of a perspective, okay? So and רבי זכריה בן הקצב,
Rabbi Zecharyah ben HaKatzav, right, so
we basically sort of were assuming this, that the sons get first,
right? That's what we were assuming when the mother dies, that you
maintain the sons' first order. רבי זכריה בן הקצב Rabbi Zecharyah ben
HaKatzav says, no,
boys and girls are equal.
Mother
dies, יחלוקו, yachloku,
boys and girls, yeah, equal. Okay, are equal. So he does not
make this דרשה derasha because he says here, it's not like when
the father dies. When the father dies, the sons get first, but
when the mother dies, they are equal. So he does not hold
of the equality of מטה אם mateh em and מטה אב. mateh
av. So by parallel, he would hold that if the son dies,
it only goes to the father, only to father, okay?
Right? Because he does not hold mother and father's tribes are equal.
People sort of see that? Okay.
What if the father's dead? Then it goes to grandfather.
Yeah, well we'll get to that. Okay. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says this is what our משנה Mishnah teaches, that that it's that
the mother never inherits, it only goes to the father, it doesn't
go to the mother. So when you want to say, "Oh, I
don't know who the author of our משנה Mishnah is, I don't
פוסקין paskin that way, I פוסקין paskin the mother inherits," why not
say it's the רבי זכריה בן הקצב Rabbi Zecharyah ben HaKatzav that
doesn't equate the מטות matot in this דרשה? derasha? So he also
wouldn't equate the מטות matot in
the top part.
Right? So that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say, okay? So
let's just try to say our משנה's Mishnah רבי זכריה בן הקצב.
Rabbi Zecharyah ben HaKatzav. He doesn't hold of the equation. He would
say that when a mother dies, they get equal. So he'll also
say when a son dies, it only goes to the father, he
doesn't hold of equating the mother and the father. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ולימא ליה רבי זכריה בן הקצב
היא דלא דריש מטות. v'leima lei Rabbi Zecharyah ben HaKatzav hi delo
darish matot. So listen: לא מצית אמרת
מתניתין כרבי זכריה בן הקצב. lo metzit amrat matnitin k'Rabbi Zecharyah ben
HaKatzav. So Michael already figured it out. You can't say the משנה's
Mishnah רבי זכריה בן הקצב Rabbi Zecharyah ben HaKatzav because then that
would mean that the משנה Mishnah would also hold of this point,
that when the mother dies, the sons and the daughters get equal.
Okay. And why can't you say that? דקתני ובני אחות, dekateni uvnei
achot, because we say that the nephews inherit from the uncle, the
mother's brother. Okay, or you set in the other way, the sister's
sons inherit. ותנא, v'tana, and a ברייתא braita explicated what the משנה
Mishnah means by that is בני אחות ולא בנות אחות, benei achot
v'lo bnot achot, the nephews and not nieces. So אמינא למאי הלכתא,
amina l'mai hilchata, what do you mean nephews and not nieces? Nieces
would get if there are no nephews. Why are you excluding nieces?
So ואמר רב ששת לקדם. v'amar Rav Sheshet l'kadem. No,
to tell you exactly that point, that the nephews get before the
nieces. All right, now if the brother is dying, if the brother
died and it's going to his sister's children, that means that the
sister is dead. Right? Okay. So if the sister is dead, then
it's passing to the sister's children through the mother, which is a
case of a mother dying. I mean she's already dead, but effectively
it's the case of a mother dying. And we're reading the משנה
Mishnah to say that it goes first to the nephews before the
nieces, which would say that when a mother dies, the sons get
first. All right. So you can't say that our משנה's Mishnah רבי
זכריה בן הקצב Rabbi Zecharyah ben HaKatzav to say only the father
inherits and that's consistent with not making this equation,
because our משנה Mishnah also assumes that the sons get first when
the mother dies. So it's not—the דרשה derasha is inconsistent. I mean
we basically are פוסקין paskin both of these to favor the men
over the women. Like you understand that when the mother dies, it's
going to maintain the sort of patriarchal order of the sons getting
first, and when the son dies, only the father will inherit. So
it's not consistent with this דרשה, derasha, but it's consistent in the
bias in favor of the sons, yes, or of the men.
So why doesn't the גמרא Gemara in raising this קשיא kashya about
the attribution to רבי זכריה בן הקצב Rabbi Zecharyah ben HaKatzav say
it's straight as the mother dies, the sons inherit first, why does
it go to nephews?
Well, I don't know, but that's—but the point is that it's an
inference from the משנה. Mishnah. So I don't know why the משנה's
Mishnah only teaching this indirectly, but I don't have an answer to
that. But anyway, but we have a ברייתא, braita, and the ברייתא
braita makes it clear that the משנה, Mishnah, by emphasizing nephews and
not nieces, the ברייתא braita makes it clear that the משנה Mishnah
is saying that even when it passes through a woman, the sons
get first. So that it can't be רבי זכריה בן הקצב. Rabbi
Zecharyah ben HaKatzav. So the point that's being made is well, once
we're saying that's true, that the sons get first when the mother
dies, and we're equating mother and father in the prioritizing, you know,
in passing down to the sons first, well then the mother should
also inherit when the son dies. We should equate mother and father
in the opposite direction as well.
God, the obvious question is then what do we דרשן? darshan?
Okay. So that's what גמרא Gemara's question is going to be. Alright
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואי סלקא דעתך דמתניתין רבי
זכריה בן הקצב היא האמר אחד הבן ואחד הבת שוין בנכסי האם
Ve-isalka da'atach de-matnitin Rabbi Zecharia Ben Katzav hi ha-amar echad haben ve-echad
habat shavin bi-nechasei ha-em that that's the son and daughters are equal
when it comes to when it's the mother's property. Okay now the
גמרא Gemara says as Michael said, דתניא נמי ממה נפשך de-tanya nami
mi-manafshach fine, so fine, so we've now said that this is the
position of רבי יהודה ברבי שמעון Rabbi Yehuda barbi Shimon when the
son dies the mother inherits, very radical and disruptive opinion. He rejects
the משנה, Mishnah, it's an opinion that differs from our משנה. Mishnah.
Fine, but our משנה Mishnah has these two פסוקים, pesukim, both of
which as I said favor the men. Okay and the גמרא Gemara's
question is, but okay, but which דרשה drasha are they following? This
דרשה drasha equates the mother to the father and says when the
mother dies the sons get first, and this says the mother is
different than the father and says when the sons die only the
father inherits. This is our משנה, Mishnah, but it doesn't follow a
particular דרשה drasha of מטות, Matot, so how does it make sense?
ממה נפשך, Mi manafshach, אי דריש i darish מטות Matot and equate
the mother with the father in terms of their property, אשה נמי
תירש את בנה, isha nami tiras es benah, so then you should
be following the position under discussion and you should say that the
same way a father inherits if his child dies the mother inherits.
אי לא דריש I lo darish מטות Matot and if you don't
have that דרשה, drasha, and so then בן קודם לבת בנכסי האם
מנלן? ben kodem le-bat bi-nechasei ha-em minalan? How do you know that
the son takes priority when the mother dies? The only way we
know that the son inherits first when it's the mother's property is
by parallel to when the father dies it's the son first. So
if you don't make this דרשה drasha and you say when the
son dies only the father inherits, father and mother are not equated,
how do you know when the mother dies to give it first
to the sons? Maybe we should divide it equally? So the גמרא
Gemara says
לעולם דריש le-olam darish מטות, Matot, it makes the דרשה drasha of
מטות, Matot, so I'm on this side of the column, and that's
why we know that when a mother dies you still get—the sons
get before daughters. Okay so how do we know—how do we know
to reject this radical idea that the mother inherits? So the
גמרא Gemara says ושני הכא דאמר קרא וכל בת יורשת נחלה, veshani
hacha de-amar kra ve-chol bat yoreshet nachala, יורשת ואינה מורשת.
yoreshet ve-eina moreshet. The דרשה drasha that says יורשת נחלה ממטות, yoreshet
nachala mi-matot, right? That is the פסוק pasuk וכל בת יורשת
נחלה ממטות. ve-chol bat yoreshet nachala mi-matot. So that word מטות Matot
in the plural tells us that this girl here, right, her mother
has property and her father has property, and they're from different tribes.
Okay right? ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, they're from different tribes. Okay
so that says that she was מטות, Matot, right? That was the
whole דרשה drasha to equate the mother and the daughter—the mother and
the father. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says in this scenario where
she has a mother and a—where we're talking about the whole mother
and father and like how it works, okay so we would say
she—it works to equate mother and father in the down direction. It
is יורשת ואינה מורשת, yoreshet ve-eina moreshet, it does not work in
the up direction. So the equation of mother and father goes when
you're going down. When the mother dies sons get first. Okay that's
where father and mother are equated when it's passing down from the
father and the mother. But if the child dies to pass up
you don't equate them. It only passes up to the father, it
doesn't pass equally to the father and the mother.
So the תירוץ tirutz to this קשיא kashya is that they דרשן
darshen מטות Matot and then there's a second דרשה drasha on another
word in the same פסוק pasuk of יורשת.
yoreshet. The מטות Matot are equated in a case of יורשת. yoreshet.
This qualifies the case of מטות. Matot.
The structure of the תירוץ tirutz is, da, you didn't get the
whole דרשה. drasha. Exactly. There's another part to the דרשה drasha that
you've forgotten. Exactly. If you don't have that all at once.
Okay
what—by דרשן darshen מטות Matot did you—did you immediately say that boys
and girls get equal or there's
another—if you don't דרשן darshen מטות Matot as
we learned that sons get first from the mother, what would be
the other option? Is that the alternative option if you don't דרשן
darshen מטות? Matot?
If you don't דרשן darshen מטות Matot then it sounds like yeah,
that when the mother dies there's no basis to say that the
sons should get before the daughters when the mother dies, unless you're
going to learn it out from the case of the father. Now
your point is maybe you learn it out by analogy, not by
a דרשה, drasha, you know, but that's—until now the גמרא Gemara's assuming
the only way to—is to fall back that without it
you would assume, I agree with you, you would assume משפחת אב
קרויה משפחה, mishpachat av kriya mishpacha, you would assume the basis, the
general assumption of prioritizing the sons. But the—as we discussed at the
time, when the mother dies you're already dealing with property that's not
part of the patriarchal family. It's already taken away from the patriarchal
family, so there might not be any purpose in that case to
give priority to the boys.
Yeah because if the daughter died, the daughter's in the father's שבט,
shevet, so preventing the mother to inherit from the daughter is keeping
it in the שבט. shevet.
Right, that's what תוספות Tosafos points out, that the idea that a
mother inherits is just significantly increasing the likelihood that the land will
go out of the שבט. shevet. Okay. Moving on. סדר נחלות. Seder
Nachalos.
So this actually, you know, the משנה Mishnah opened by a nice
cat I mean, well, it’s I mean for once I would actually
say, you know, sometimes like משנה, Mishnah, a פרק perek or a
new topic starts from some total left field place and only deep
into the פרק perek or deep into the מסכת maseches do you
get like a nice conceptual framework. Ours actually started with a nice
conceptual framework. נוחלין ומנחילין, Nochlin ve-Manchilin, מנחילין ונוחלין, Manchilin ve-Nochlin, נוחלין ומנחילין,
Nochlin u-Manchilin, okay,
but now actually it turns right afterwards to the פסוקים. psukim. All
right, so actually, you know, maybe this could have been first, like
we like starting with the פסוקים, psukim, but still I think this
פרק perek is very nicely organized. I actually, by the way, misspoke
the other day. I think I was saying that, you know, that
the idea of sort of the rabbinic institutions, the various structures or
types of rabbinic wills, are coming up in the later פרקים. prakim.
They actually come up later in this פרק. perek. This פרק perek
is so big, it’s 30 דף daf I think or something like
that. So anyway, so even this is a very large פרק perek
and we’re going to, after we get through the issues of inheritance,
we’re going to get to the issue of wills. Okay, but anyway
let’s take a look. סדר נחלות כך הוא. Seder Nachalos kach hu.
Here’s the order, here’s the priority, because our first משנה Mishnah told
us who can inherit from whom, but it didn’t prioritize. The גמרא
Gemara laid out the order, but the משנה Mishnah didn’t. So here
the משנה Mishnah is laying it out. Okay, איש כי ימות ובן
אין לו והעברתם את נחלתו לבתו. Ish ki yamut u-ven ein lo
ve-ha’avartem et nachalato le-vito. Let’s just read the פסוקים. psukim. First the
son, no son then the daughter. בן קודם לבת. Ben kodem le-vas.
So the son comes before the daughter. Now here’s the next here’s
the חידוש chiddush of the משנה. Mishnah. כל יוצאי ירכו של בן,
Kol yotzei yerecho shel ben, all of the issue of the loins
of the son, okay, which basically is a very specific phrase. It
doesn’t mean his relatives, it means his direct descendants.
All of the direct descendants of the
son קודמין לבת, kodmin le-vas, come before the daughter. So this is
the basic principle that children and grandchildren and great-great-great-great-great-grandchildren are all considered
to be a replacement of the person who died. Okay, so the
principle sort of is, you know, תוספות Tosafos says, why don’t we
just use a general principle of בני בנים הרי הם כבנים, bnei
banim harei hem ke-vanim, right? You know, that grandchildren are like children,
that you go down generations, it’s all considered a continuation of the
person. תוספות Tosafos has an interesting question, do we always say that
concept or not? He says maybe we say it more when the
פסוקים psukim use the word זרע. zera. זרע zera is an issue
which might indicate like not an immediate first generation, but like any,
you know, descendant. בן ben maybe it’s not so obvious we include
grandchildren and so on. But anyway, but that’s the basic point here,
that so if we have the priority of
any person who comes first on the list, who comes who comes
like, it’s your turn on the list, this person, right? Number one
is the son, okay, and number two is the daughter in terms
of the order of inheritance, okay, so before we move over to
a number two on the list, we’re going to look for any
descendant, right? Any descendant, it doesn’t matter how many generations down, it
doesn’t matter boy or girl, right? Any descendant before we move on
to the next to the next number on the list. Okay, so
that’s the basic principle.
כל יוצאי ירכו של בן קודמין לבת. Kol yotzei yerecho shel ben
kodmin le-vas. Yep.
Do you mean any male No I do not.
I mean any descendant, boy or girl, okay? You could have way
down here a
great-great-great-great-great-great-great-granddaughter,
granddaughter, and she comes before the actual daughter. Now that sounds ironic,
right? The okay, they’re both girls, this is a girl that’s closer
to the actual deceased, but the point is no, because this takes
the place of her her
great-great-great-great-great-grandfather.
ירכו, Yerecho, כל יוצאי ירכו, kol yotzei yerecho, right. Okay, question.
What
if, you know like, let's say the grand let’s say this son
had a son and then a daughter. Yeah. In other words, and
then that son died with that you know let’s say there was
a daughter over here, right, but then this person, you know, had
a great-great-granddaughter, would that great-granddaughter come before this daughter over here?
Yeah. Wait a minute. Oh oh, no. That’s a good question. Okay,
Michael Michael asks a good question. Michael says, let’s say he has
a son and a daughter, okay, and his son died. Okay, so
you don’t keep on going down through the son, meaning before you
go down to the because we’re in the category here of the
next generation takes the place of the you’re right, it’s a little
funny, right, because normally we sort of here have this preference of
son over daughter, but but no, but before I’m almost 100 percent
sure, I’ll double check, that since it’s on the idea that it’s
taking the place of the father, we’re not we’re sort of like
gender blind here, and because we’re gender blind, right, any any boy
anybody here what would take what?
But except that the boy will inherit בנחלה binchala first.
Yeah, that's true, meaning if they're both alive, it's all going to
pass on to the grandson and not the granddaughter.
The boy, that little boy there, the second generation he pre-deceases his
sisters. Right?
Right. But Jenna's point is if they're both alive, we're not totally
gender-blind. If they're both alive, then the then the grandson gets before...
I gotta check this actually.
Meaning that guy, the son, what? Meaning that guy who dies, his
his kids are going to inherit his stuff,
his own property,
but they won't inherit the grandfather's.
But if he gets, let me make this clear. If somebody dies
and it passes down, then when this guy dies, it's considered like
his property. You don't go back and look at where he got
it from. The issue of sort of going down this is when
people are dead along this line at the time of this death.
But I need to double-check this because you're asking a really good
question, which is how
gender-blind are we when we start going down? If they're both alive,
does the grandson get before the granddaughter? I'm pretty positive the answer
is yes. Okay, but what was the other question?
If the grandson
dies, do you prefer this line over that line? Okay, I
gotta check this. All right, let's see. You guys are like one
degree of complexity beyond where the משנה mishna or I am up
to right now. Yes.
Probably they didn't have lifespans long enough to have that happen.
I know, but we still deal with it theoretically.
If the purpose is to keep within the tribe, then why would
the granddaughter receive rather than the sister up here?
Yeah, so the difference is you're right. Meaning the initial structure is
to keep within the tribe, but once we... You're right. There's a
funny logic. You could say since the preference of the boys to
the girls is to keep within the tribe, we should only have
this rule for sons or for male descendants. Yeah, I mean you're
right, it sort of violates that logic again. I mean that's interesting.
See what בנות צלפחד benot Tzelofchad did? They messed it up! So
disruptive where it's going so many different ways.
It's like the joint bank account
that we were talking about a couple... Right, exactly. But of course
when the person dies, it could be direct automatic. Oh, it's going
to go to a great-great-granddaughter who's married to whatever. Anyway, or it
doesn't even have to be that. It would be this person's daughter's
son would be of a different tribe. Right? And if he was
dead and his daughter was dead, it would automatically go to a
son of a different tribe. Okay. כל יוצאי ירכו של בן קודמין
לבת. Kol yotzei yerecho shel ben kodmin labat. בת קודמת לאחים. Bat
kodemet lachin. Okay, so now
so that's number two. After that, the number three is brothers.
I have to figure out a different line that means married and
one that means brothers. Okay.
A double line.
Yeah, a double line means married. Okay, fine. Anyway, number three is
brothers. Okay. יוצאי ירכה של בת קודמין לאחים. Yotzei yerecha shel bat
kodmin lachin. Wait, wait, wait,
the משנה mishna doesn't have the father. The גמרא gemara inserts the
father. Okay. בת קודמת לאחים. Bat kodemet lachin. יוצאי ירכה
של בת קודמין לאחים Yotzei yerecha shel bat kodmin lachin before you
go onto the brothers, you look if she has any issue. Okay.
אחים קודמין לאחי האב. Achin kodmin l'achei ha'av.
Brothers here come before the father's brothers. This is the deceased, okay?
So it's the deceased's brothers and then the deceased's father's brothers.
So you really gotta find a dead
person.
So that's uncle here. Then okay, father, okay. So
the deceased... first whatever, children, then brother, then uncle. Now of course,
it's not really then uncle. What the משנה mishna leaves out is
father. Now you would think father goes here like 3B, but if
you remember before, actually father gets inserted here. Okay, but the משנה
mishna ignores father. Okay.
Between daughter and brother. I'll explain why in a minute, we'll get
to it.
Okay.
יוצאי ירכו של אחים קודמין לאחי האב. Yotzei yerecho shel achin kodmin
l'achei ha'av. זה הכלל. Ze haklal. כל הקודם בנחלה. Kol hakodem binchala.
Anybody that's earlier in the list, in the order, יוצאי ירכו קודמין.
Yotzei yerecho kodmin. Any issue comes before you move on to the
next sort of category in the list. והאב קודם לכל יוצאי ירכו.
Veha'av kodem lechol yotzei yerecho.
Okay, I lied when I said the father wasn't here. He is
here. Okay, but he wasn't here sort of inserted in that order.
The father now here's the father comes before any of his issue.
So what does that mean? So, no, so, here שא, sha, quiet.
Okay, so he dies. Okay, his father comes before any of his
father's children. So what does that mean? His father comes before who
are his father's children? Brother,
the brother, right? So if the father comes before any of the
father's descendants, right, then then the then the father is actually going
to get
here, right?
2A. Yeah, whatever. This is 2A and this is 2B. Okay. So
the father is going to get before the brother. And the logic
is cause he's related to his brother really only through his father,
if you think about it that way, right? So the father actually
so goes to his son, his daughter, his father, okay, his brother,
and then now it doesn't go after his brother, guess what? It
doesn't if there's no brother and it's not going to go to
his uncle, who's it going to go to before his uncle? Can
anybody figure this out? If he if no brother, no children, no
brother, no children, no father, no brother goes to his uncle, but
actually before the uncle it goes to grandfather because it's going to
go to the father before so the actual order of it goes
like, I don't know if this is going to help, but anyway,
it goes down, okay, it goes down, then it goes up, okay,
and then it goes down again, okay? And then you just repeat
that. Alright. So children, father, you know, siblings. And then if that
didn't work, right then you just repeat it again, right? You go
up and then you go down. Then go up and then you
go down. Okay. So anyway, that sort of that's how it works.
Now, and the logic is and the real point of it is
that you only really have to know two rules. You really have
to just know two rules. You know what the two rules are?
First to, you know, first children and then father. Okay. And once
you know that, it all works. Why? I mean children is like
son, son, then daughter, and then father. Okay. And those are really
the only two rules you have to know. First it goes to
the son, I mean and then passes down, you have to know
the rule of going passing down. No son goes to the daughter,
no daughter passes down. None of those goes to the father, no
father what's the next thing you do? No father oh so we
so we go back here. Right? If these are the only two
rules we have, if there's no father then it goes to the
father's first son which is his father's. If the father doesn't have
sons it goes to the father's daughters which are his sisters, right?
And then anyone down in the line. And if there's no son
or daughter then it goes to the father's father.
So it's basically just as far as you can go down until
you can't and you go back up another.
Son and then daughter, son and then daughter and then father and
if no father then you then repeat. Okay. Rinse lather repeat, rinse
lather repeat. Okay.
But it doesn't go it doesn't go down and then up it
keeps going down as far as it can go down when it
can't go down anymore it goes up to the next generation up.
Right. Correct. Jenny you had a question.
Yeah, the language of קודם לכל יוצאי ירכו kodem lechol yotzei yeracho
doesn't quite line up here. Right.
Because this is יוצאי ירכו. yotzei yeracho. Yeah, you're you're absolutely correct.
You're absolutely correct. The phrase קודם לכל יוצאי ירכו kodem lechol yotzei
yeracho is not helpful. It really should have been קודם kodem to
the next to his direct descendant. Okay, the רשבם Rashbam says it,
you're right, it's imprecise. Okay.
When does it go to the uncle?
It goes to the uncle if there is no no children, no
father, no brothers, no sisters, no grandfather, no grandfather then it goes
to the uncle.
Okay? Because the the uncle in effect is gone through the grandfather.
So like I said this is really it. Sons and then sons,
you know, sons let's say, you know, sons plus, you know, going
down, daughters everybody is plus, okay, but the father isn't plus. Sons
going all the way down, daughters going all the way down, father,
no father then you know you go back up here, right? Zip
whatever zip and then you keep on just repeat. Okay. Alright.
So
let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan בן ובן
אין לו. ben uven ein lo. So this is what we're going
to do with how do you know that you go all the
way down the line
first. אין לי אלא בן. ein li ela ben. בן בת הבן
ben bat ha-ben trips over the tongue easier than בת בת הבן.
bat bat ha-ben. Okay, but anyway, מניין, minayin, how do I know
you keep on going down the line?
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, אין לו, ein lo, ובן אין לו. u-ven
ein lo. So the דרשה drasha is עיין עליו. Ayen alav אין,
Ain, עיין. ayen Investigate. So investigate any descendants, you know, would be
considered to be a continuation.
Right, בת. bat. So it says והעברתם את נחלתו לבתו. ve-ha'avartem et
nachalato levito. So if there's nobody down that line, go to the
daughter. אין לי אלא בת. Ain li ela bat. I only know
if he's got a daughter. בת הבת bat ha-bat או בן הבת
o ben ha-bat או בת בן הבת. o bat ben ha-bat. מניין?
Minayin? How do I know if he's, if he's got, you know,
if his daughter's got kids or grandkids? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, אין
לו ein lo from the son. We're using the דרשה drasha from
the son to now to apply to the daughter, right? No, is
it ואין לו בת? ve-ein lo bat? והעברתם את נחלתו לבתו. ve-ha'avartem
et nachalato levito. Yeah, ואין לו בת. ve-ein lo bat. It says
אין לו ein lo by the daughter as well. עיין עליו ayen
alav or it should be עיין עליה. ayen aleha. Anyway, I guess
עיין ayen. עליו alav. the deceased.
Anyway, that's the craziest דרשה.
drasha. Fine. כיצד? Keitzad? What can I tell you? כיצד? Keitzad? So
what does this mean?
נחלה ממשמשת והולכת nachala memashmeshet ve-holechet עד ראובן. ad Reuven. Okay, so
you keep on going, you know, down and down the generations, down
the daughter's generations, up to the father, then father's children, right? So
it'd be any brothers, any of their descendants, any sisters, any of
their descendants. Nope, go up. So you keep on going up and
down and up and down and up and down, eventually, we're all
related, you're going to find somebody who's related. Okay? So and you
go all the way up back to the אבות, avot, back to
ראובן בן יעקב. Reuven ben Yaakov. Okay? Do you know even if
you have to go all—now, all the way up, you eventually will
find somebody else who is, you know, who's related to you. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says ולימא עד יעקב. ve-leima ad Yaakov. Why
don't you say that it goes all the way back up to
יעקב? Yaakov? So the גמרא Gemara says no. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye:
גמירי דלא כליא שבטא. gmiri de-la kalya shivta. No, no, no, because
that would mean that a tribe would be completely deceased from בני
ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, would be, would have completely stopped to exist. If
there is no
descendants of ראובן, Reuven, so you had to go up to יעקב,
Yaakov, and then יעקב Yaakov isn't alive, so we're going to have
to now transfer to another tribe, right? And go down, you know,
that chart over at that edge, at—people sort of see how that
would work. You'd keep on going up, right? That would mean that
there would be no, nobody within ראובן. Reuven. As long as there's
somebody in the same tribe, you're all related to ראובן. Reuven. You
know, we're all related—everybody who's a לוי Levi is all related, is
all some descendant of לוי. Levi. So, you know, you'll always find
that—so to go over to a tribe means that that tribe will
have ceased to exist, and we don't, we believe that that will
not happen. Of course, ten of the tribes were sent into exile
by סנחריב. Sancheriv. Right, they're lost, they're not dead, right, but you
know, but that's the point. You always say we couldn't find any
surviving heirs; it doesn't mean they don't exist.
But yes, or at the end of ספר שופטים, Sefer Shoftim,
the tribe of בנימין Binyamin almost ceased to exist.
Ah, but that's why, but we know it won't happen. Yes.
Just a point—is there a timeframe for this? In other words, how
long are we going to wait until, like, you know, someone—how long,
you know, is there a timeframe? Like, you know, mean a year?
We, you know, you mean we can't find any heirs, what are
we going to do with the property? And we've looked and looked
and looked and looked and looked. You know, I don't know, it's
a good question. What are we supposed to do with the property?
Who's supposed to own it now? Is it supposed to be הפקר?
hefker? I mean, I don't know, it's a good question in American
law. I mean, I guess in American law the government takes it
over, right? Does anybody know?
There have actually been complicated court cases, not just with individuals who
die and who knows who their heirs are, but churches where the
last member dies before they figured out what to do with the
property.
Oh wow. Okay, so anyway, so I don't know the answer to
that. Okay, so אמר רב הונא אמר רב: Amar Rav Huna amar
Rav: כל האומר תירש בת עם בת הבן. Kol ha-omer tirash bat
im bat ha-ben. If anybody were to say that a daughter—so here,
let's make this a little bit easier. Okay, here's—this is the paradox
or the irony, that he is not around, his daughter will come
before his sister. Okay, a granddaughter will come before a daughter. So,
that's a little ironic. So the גמרא Gemara is pointing out: so
if somebody says once a granddaughter is getting it, it should be
split equally with a daughter, meaning rejects this whole—this principle: תירש בת
עם בת הבן, tirash bat im bat ha-ben, what?
Right, עם בת הבן, im bat ha-ben, אפילו נשיא שבישראל, afilu nasi
she-be-Yisrael, even if he was like the, you know, the leader, the
patriarch of ישראל, Yisrael, אין שומעין לו. ein shomin lo. It doesn't
matter, he doesn't have any authority. That is a completely rejected opinion.
שאינם אלא מצדוקין. she-einam ela mi-Tzedukin. That is a Sadducean position. Okay?
And therefore, it's completely illegitimate. Now, what does it mean completely—and therefore
we have so, you know, assigned it as a—it can't even be
a legitimate דעת יחיד. da'at yachid. Right? I mean, you know, we've
had some radical opinions here, right? We've had opinions that the mother's
property is divided
equally. That that
once it's going down to a granddaughter then the then the daughter
is
also also gets gets it. Okay. They're all daughters anyway. They're all
daughters they're all daughters anyway. So this is a less radical position
than we've had before. But historically, it was a Sadducean position. So
because historically it was a Sadducean position, it's completely illegitimate for anybody
to hold of it, right? So that's interesting. That happens sometimes because
of some historical, you know, whatever context certain things are seen as
like taboo and off-limits and so on. All right. Now, what does
this mean? So the רשב״ם *Rashbam* just says it means like he's
פוסק *posek* this way, but it's completely illegitimate פסק *psak*. תוספות Tosafos
*Tosfos*, so what's the נשיא Nasi *Nasi*? What's the special role of
a נשיא *Nasi* in פסק *psak*? So the רשב״ם *Rashbam* says well,
it means he's gotten together a big בית דין *beis din*, but
anyway look at תוספות Tosafos. *Tosfos*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* says that מר
*Mar* is going even further. אפילו נשיא שבישראל *Afilu Nasi she-beYisrael*, שרוצה
לתקן *she-rotzeh letaken*, לפי צורך שעה *lefi tzorech shaah*. He's not even
claiming it's real הלכה halacha *halacha*. He's just saying we're going to
for whatever societal purposes, we're going to establish a rabbinic ordinance that
in this case a granddaughter and daughter will get together. Okay, כמשמצינו
בבני בנימין *ke-she-matzinu bi-vnei Binyamin*, שהתנו שלא תירש בת בין אחים *she-hitnu
she-lo tirash bat bein achim*. We're going to get to that later.
אין שומעין לו משום צדוקים Tzedukim *ein shomin lo mishum Tzadukim*. So
not only do you reject it as a possible פסק *psak* and
a דרשה drasha. *drasha* of the פסוקים pesukim *psukim*, you don't even
allow it as a rabbinic institution or תקנה *takkanah*, even a temporary
one, because it's associated with a Sadducean position. All right. So it's
really interesting sort of the political dimension here, right, of these פסקים
*psakim* or of these discussions. Yes. So now we're going to see
where it's how is it a Sadducean position.
I don't think I understand that פסק *psak* though. Like what would
it be? It would go to the daughter? According to the פסוקים
Pesukim *psukim* first
it goes to the son. Right. If there's no son, it goes
to the son's children. Right. But if the only surviving children of
the son or the only children of the son are girls, are
daughters, so as long as you're going to be giving it to
daughters through the son, then you should be giving it to then
you should be giving it to the deceased's daughters as well. You
mean
divide it. Divide it. Yeah. If if a granddaughter is getting it,
the daughter should also get it. And you divide it equally.
As opposed to going down the line.
As opposed to giving to a granddaughter and the daughter getting nothing.
Right. Which is what the הלכה *halacha* is.
Yeah. So the thing is that even if though we generally have
a rule of let's say הפקר בית דין הפקר
*hefker beis din hefker*, and they probably
could take it away, so if this בית דין *beis din* wants
to sit down and do that like they could.
Right. Exactly. Exactly. We are not allowing anybody to ever recognize... maybe
part of the reason is it's so it's such a
persuasive argument that you really have to make it totally off-limits, you
know? So, okay. And we're not allowing that as a פסק *psak*
and we're not allowing that as a תקנה *takkanah* because it's a
Sadducean position. Okay. ואינה אלא מעשה צדוקים Tzadukim *ve-einah ella maaseh Tzadukim*.
דתניא *De-tanya*, בעשרים וארבעה בטבת *be-esrim ve-arba be-Tevet*, on the 24th of
this is from מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit, *Megillat Taanit*. All right, I
meant to bring in I have an academic version of מגילת תענית
Megillat Ta'anit *Megillat Taanit*. I might have it there.
You got it? Yeah. Want to bring it up? Okay. So here's
what it says. What so מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit *Megillat Taanit* are
actually the days which you are not... pass it up... are actually
the days it's very ancient, it's from the time of בית שני
*Bayis Sheni*, and it's also, you know, a very early like written
thing that was not scripture, that was, you know, because everything was
oral that wasn't scripture, and it's a list of the days that
you are not allowed to fast. People know like because they are
like minor holidays. In the Middle Ages like the church declared a
lot of minor holidays and said that you're not allowed to have
you're not allowed to have war on those days. It was a
way of cutting down on some of the crazy violence of the
Middle Ages. Anyway, so these are like minor holidays that you're not
allowed to fast. Of course, חנוכה *Chanukah* is the one is part
of מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit *Megillat Taanit* that is well known. Most
of the days we have no recollection of because they were all
בית שני *Bayis Sheni* related and there's a whole discussion in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about בטלה מגילת תענית Megillas Taanis *batlah Megillat Taanit*,
but anyway, but it's all really interesting as a source of historical
data. So this is like an academic version of it. There's actually
two parts of it. There's the מגילה *Megillah* itself, and then there's
the סכוליון *skolion* which is... scolios... scolion... scolion. Anyway, which is like
the sort of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* on מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit.
*Megillat Taanit*. Anyway,
so anyway so here it is. Let me just see. So what
day is it? So it's
what 24th of...
I mean I think that you mean like when did we start
having like manuscripts or whatever? I don't know, it's a good question.
I don't know. Okay, so here's what here's what this text says.
Okay, בעשרים ושמונה בטבת *be-esrim ve-shmona be-Tevet*. I'll read this one first.
Okay. Okay. No, this is... Oh, this is the 24th. Okay. בעשרים
וארבעה בטבת *be-esrim ve-arba be-Tevet*, the 24th of of טבת Tevet. *Tevet*,
תבנא לדיננא *tavna le-dinana*. תבנא לדיננא, we returned to our ruling, we
returned to the original ruling. שהיו צדוקים אומרים, shehayu tzedukim omrim,
now it sounds like now we're going to the language of the,
of the ברייתא, braita, we've left מגילת תענית, Megillat Ta'anit. because מגילת
תענית is Aramaic. It's funny, normally you know the original text is
Hebrew and the Aramaic is the גמרא's Gemara gloss on the original
statement, but מגילת תענית was written in Aramaic. So now you have
the תנא's Tanna gloss or elaboration on the מגילת תענית which was
in Aramaic. Okay, so anyway, שהיו צדוקים אומרים, shehayu tzedukim omrim, תירש
הבת עם בת הבן. tirash habat im bat haben.
The צדוקים Tzadukim used to say let a daughter inherit with a
granddaughter through the son. נטפל להם רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. nitpal lahem
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai
was like assigned to them or he like, you know, he he
he... He infiltrated them. Well, not infiltrated. נטפל nitpal means like the
word of טפל. tafel. It sort of means like yeah, to deal
with them, but it's also a little bit of a dismissive tone.
Like you know, I, that's what I always read it, like he's
like just go deal with them. Okay, what do you think? Michal,
you think he has a different sense? Go take care of them.
Yeah, go take care of them. Go deal with them. Right. Exactly.
Oh really, that's what's used for child care? טיפול. tipul. Ah, right.
I, that's what I think.
There's something dismissive about that verb.
If there's also, go take care of this.
Ah, really?
Okay, deal with it. Right. Okay. נטפל להם רבן יוחנן בן זכאי.
nitpal lahem Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. So אמר להם, amar lahem, שוטים,
shotim, מניין לכם? minayin lachem?
Idiots, where do you know this from? ולא היה אדם שהחזירו דבר.
v'lo haya adam shehechiziru davar. Nobody was willing to get into a
fight with him, who was willing to to articulate where what their
basis is. חוץ מזקן אחד, chutz m'zaken echad, except for one old
guy שהיה מפטפט כנגדו, shehaya mefatpet knegdo,
like he was like, you know, that's also like a very dismissive
word. He was chattering, he was chattering. Do you remember though before
when we had, you know, יתרו שהיה מפטפט Yitro shehaya mefatpet or
יוסף מפטפט בייתרו? Yosef mefatpet b'Yitro? Anyway, שהיה מפטפט כנגדו ואומר, shehaya
mefatpet knegdo v'omer, ומה בת בנו הבאה מכח בנו תירשנו? u'mah bat
bno haba'ah mikoch bno tirashenu?
The granddaughter that only comes through the son
will inherit him. בתו הבאה מכוחו, bito haba'ah mikocho, his daughter directly
that comes directly from him, לא כל שכן? lo kol sheken? Certainly
so, if a daughter is getting it, so why does a granddaughter
who is one degree removed get it before before before a daughter?
It's a pretty good argument. So קרא עליו את המקרא הזה. kara
alav et hamikra hazeh. So he read him the following פסוק. pasuk.
רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי.
Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai.
אלה בני שעיר החורי יושבי הארץ, eleh bnei Se'ir haChori yoshvei ha'aretz,
these are the children or the sons of Se'ir the Chori who
dwellers of the land. לוטן ושובל וצבעון
וענה. Lotan v'Shoval v'Tzivon v'Anah. Okay. וכתיב, uch'tiv, in another פסוק pasuk
says, ואלה בני צבעון ואיה וענה. v'eleh bnei Tzivon v'Ayah v'Anah.
So ענה Anah here is, is he a sibling of צבעון, Tzivon,
a descendant a child of שעיר, Se'ir, or is he a child
of צבעון? Tzivon? Right? You see how the same word appears as
a child and as a sibling. אלא מלמד שבא צבעון על אמו
והוליד ענה. ela melamed sheba Tzivon al imo v'holid Anah.
Okay, so the way you can have both a sibling and a
child is the person had intercourse with his mother. So therefore ענה
Anah is both his child and his sibling. Okay, now what does
that have to do with anything? So so first the גמרא says,
ודילמא תרי ענה הוו? u'dilma terei Anah havu? Maybe there are two
Anahs? אמר רבא, amar Rava, אמינא
מילתא דלא אמר שבור מלכא. amina milta d'lo amar Shvor Malka.
I set to explain this an idea that even the like head
of the Persian government did not say. Now why are you mentioning
שבור מלכא? Shvor Malka? So you know, the רשב"ם Rashbam says it
really means the גמרא says ומנו שמואל. umano Shmuel. So what
why are you calling שמואל Shmuel שבור מלכא? Shvor Malka? But because
we rule like שמואל Shmuel with דיני ממונות dinei mamonot and שבור
מלכא Shvor Malka is like a powerful suggests power. So like I
said something that even the most powerful, you know, authority in דיני
ממונות dinei mamonot did not say to explain this דרשה. drasha Oh,
that's echoing the נשיא maybe, maybe. Okay, so איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri,
in some say, אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, אמינא מילתא דלא
אמר שבור מלכא ומנו רבא. amina milta d'lo amar Shvor Malka umano
Rava. So no, it was a different generation. רב פפא Rav Papa
said a same phrase and was referring to רבא. Rava. I said
a פשט pshat in this that even great authorities did not say.
How what's this like it such a like it matters so much
this reading of this פסוק? pasuk? But anyway,
how do you know it's the same ענה? Anah? אמר קרא, amar
kra, הוא ענה. hu Anah. הוא ענה אשר מצא את הימים במדבר
ברעותו את החמורים לצבעון אביו. hu Anah asher matza et hayemim bamidbar
bir'oto et hachamorim l'Tzivon aviv. So הוא ענה דמעיקרא. hu Anah d'mei'ikara.
Since it says הוא ענה, hu Anah, it's the פסוק pasuk is
telling you it's the same ענה, Anah, the same ענה Anah that
we mentioned as a child of צבעון Tzivon is also a child
of שעיר. Se'ir. And therefore the only way it's possible is is
that he had intercourse with his mother and his child is his
sibling. Now, what what does this have to do with anything?
So
which is sort of what the צדוקי Tzeduki said back.
אמר ליה רבי בכך אתה פוטרני? amar leh Rebbi b'kach atah potreni?
What that's an answer? Now, okay, before we go on, it might
be a bad answer but we have to understand that it is
an answer. What type of an answer is it? So first thing
you have to know תוספות Tosafos. actually has a very lovely תוספות.
תוספות says ענה Anah first of all you have to know is
a woman, not a man. Okay? So and he tries to show
it from various פסוקים and so on. So if we accept that
ענה Anah is a woman,
sure מצה, matzah, sure,
sure, sure, I don't know, read תוספות. I don't know what to
tell you. Okay, so if ענה Anah is a woman, okay, so
there you have, so here we have שעיר, Seir,
צבעון, Tzivon,
and
ענה. Anah. How is it spelled? אלף Aleph נון nun הא? hey?
עין? Ayin? עין נון הא. Ayin nun hey. Okay, ענה. Anah. So,
so, it says that, it says that she, now it also sort
of recognizes her as a sibling, okay? So for what purpose is
it recognizing her as a sibling, especially since we've established that צבעון
Tzivon is her father, and now we're talking about inheritance because it
says יושבי הארץ? yoshvei ha'aretz? So יושבי הארץ yoshvei ha'aretz means that
they inherit the land, okay? It's all non-Jews, but that's besides the
point. Okay, so to what purpose, if we're looking at it and
we understand in the context of inheritance, are we saying that they're
equal since since we've said that ענה Anah is really, it's not
שעיר Seir is not the father? Ah, but if צבעון, Tzivon, but
remember it has all the other siblings here as well. Who are
the other siblings?
Whatever, לוטן Lotan and שובל Shoval etc. So if צבעון Tzivon isn't
around, then ענה Anah is equally inherits together with these guys, why?
And she's a she, because she's taking the place of צבעון Tzivon
her father. So she's mentioned as a child of שעיר Seir in
this list to say that she will get equal inheritance, not because
she genuinely is a child,
she's actually צבעון Tzivon's child, you know, צבעון Tzivon is her father,
but by virtue of צבעון Tzivon and taking the place of צבעון,
Tzivon, she's actually going to inherit equally.
But doesn't
the דרשה drasha.
support the
צדוקי Tzaduki's position? No, why?
Because there are brothers and and she is taking the place of
a brother. And if they had sisters, their sisters are not getting,
okay? If they had sisters here, Rachel, okay, she's not getting. But
ענה, Anah, a granddaughter, is getting.
Oh, because it's the ענה Anah that's down below.
Exactly, exactly. She's treated as a as a first generation child and
as a first generation son because she's a descendant because she's a
child of צבעון. Tzivon. That's the דרשה.
drasha And what is he saying? That in all these הלכות נחלה,
hilchos nachala, ממזרים mamzerim are
like, the status of being a ממזר mamzer has no relevance? They
inherit like everybody else.
That is correct. We haven't mentioned that yet, but that is correct.
And
it comes from the father, right?
Right. Okay. What? So yeah.
But none
of these folks are Jews.
Yeah, so somehow we're assuming that you can infer from that. Okay,
and let's just finish this point. All right, ששש shhh people, I
want to just finish this and I want to read from the
מגילת תענית itself. I haven't checked, but we'll see if it says
the same thing. אמר לו שוטה. Amar lo shoteh. So he says
בכך אתה פוטרני, bakacha ata potreni, what that דרשה drasha is going
to prove something? אמר לו שוטה ולא תהא תורה שלמה שלנו כשיחה
בטלה שלכם. Amar lo shoteh velo tehei torah sheleimah shelanu kesichah bateilah
shelachem. You know, fine, that was just to to to show how
how dismissively I treat you, okay? That I'm willing to do some
funny דרשה with צבעון Tzivon to prove my point, but you know,
our weighty תורה, Torah, our תורה, Torah, you know, it shouldn't even
be in conversation with your נארשקייט. narishkeit. All right, so what's the
answer? So here's the answer. And again, it seems like a pretty
reasonable position, but anyway here's the answer. מה לבת בנו שכן יפה
כחה, Mah levas beno shekein yafeh koachah,
yeah, he's saying this. This is the real argument. This is רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי Rebbi Yochanan ben Zakai is saying this is the
real argument that you know that a granddaughter gets before a daughter
in this scenario. מה לבת בנו, Mah levas beno, a daughter of
a son, שכן יפה כחה במקום האחים. shekein yafeh koachah bemakom ha'achim.
So her she is considered to be equivalent with the brothers, which
what does that mean? That sort of is like begging the question,
okay? תאמר בבתו שהורע כחה במקום אחים. Tomar bevito shehoreiah koachah bemakom
achim.
Okay,
would you say by the daughter that's not equivalent to the brothers?
But that seems to also be sort of like a that seems
to also like be begging the question, right? That's exactly the point.
The point is how you know that a son's daughter is equivalent
to the brothers? You know, you're just stating it, you're not proving
it. So the רשב"ם Rashbam basically says that the proof was from
בנות צלפחד. Bnos Tzelafchad. And I'll say it in a minute, but
let's just finish the point. So it's not exactly clear how he's
proving it, he's just sort of stating it. אותו היום נצחום ועשאוהו
יום טוב. Oso hayom nitzchum va'asa'uhu yom tov. And that day they
somehow were victorious and, you know, even though the צדוקים were in
a position of power, somehow... Maybe got the צדוקים to concede the
point and this became established as the הלכה that a granddaughter through
a son comes before a daughter. So let me first see first
of all if we have it in this מגילת תענית. This is,
hold on.
It doesn't say what the actual...
No.
No, it doesn't actually have this in the original מגילת תענית. What'd
it say? Wait, wait. It says טבת.
Tevet. Twenty-fourth of טבת.
Yeah, it only has the twenty-eighth and it has a different holiday.
So I don't know. Okay, anyway, that's... I should have checked beforehand.
It has another very different holiday. It has similar language, מפטפט mefatphet
and whatever, but it was a completely different scenario. Anyway, let me
just tell you what the רשב"ם Rashbam says is the... is the
proof, which wasn't actually stated. It was from בנות צלפחד. Benos Tzelofchad.
Okay, because בנות צלפחד Benos Tzelofchad were... so בנות צלפחד, Benos Tzelofchad,
we should actually write out their names. But anyway, here's צלפחד Tzelofchad
and who was צלפחד's Tzelofchad father? חפר, Chefer, right? Okay, and then
צלפחד Tzelofchad had these... had these uncles and his uncles basically said
like, "Hey, you know," they came and complained and they said fine,
you have to marry in the tribe etc. So the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam basically says is that what happened was is that they're
all inheriting from חפר. Chefer. Now that's... the פסוקים aren't clear, like
they haven't even gotten into the land, right? Okay, but if we
imagine that it's not like צלפחד Tzelofchad had the property and then
they inherited. צלפחד Tzelofchad has died. All of these people are going
to inherit from חפר. Chefer. That's going to be a whole question.
Who are seen as the heirs to the land? A guy goes
in with his sons and grandchildren etc. and you have to, you
know, at the time of יהושע, Yehoshua, who is the original owner
of the land? So if we assume that חפר Chefer is conceptually
the one who inherits his plot in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so
then if they're getting, they're getting with there being brothers. There are
brothers that are still alive, their uncles, and they are actually getting
in צלפחד's Tzelofchad position. You see that? Like we are making this
case the case of בנות צלפחד. Benos Tzelofchad. Okay, that there's no
father and they're taking it in the presence of brothers. So if
daughters... if granddaughters can get in the presence of brothers, we know
that a sister would be excluded, right? So a sister's excluded, but
a granddaughter through a father divides with the brother, very tough. So
it's... if that's... so it wasn't stated, but the argument is that's
the case of בנות צלפחד. Benos Tzelofchad. Why'd you say that?
I don't know.